阿姆斯特丹大约四分之一的地表面积都被水覆盖。
Roughly a quarter of the surface area of Amsterdam is covered in water.
165条运河贯穿全城，总长超过100公里，
165 canals run over 100 km throughout the city
1200多座桥梁让城市适合步行和骑行。
and more than 1200 bridges make it walkable or bikable.
其中大部分是在一个世纪之内建成的，
Most of it was built in the span of a single century
其发展可以简化为几个特定阶段。
and its growth can be simplified into a couple specific stages.
>> 阿姆斯特丹更像是一座经过精心规划的城市，
>> Amsterdam is much more of a planned city
而且有很多限制条件。
and there's a lot of constraints.
我觉得
The way people deal with these constraints are very interesting,
人们应对这些限制的方式非常有趣。
I think.
当你开始理解每个区域背后的动机时，
And when you start to understand the motivations for each section,
你就能像读书一样读懂这张地图。
you can read the map like a book.
我们到阿姆斯特丹了，
We made it to Amsterdam
这里太美了。
and it is so beautiful.
我很兴奋能制作这期视频，
I am so excited to make this video
因为这是我期待已久的一期。
because this is one I've been looking forward to for a long time.
老实说，目前我对这座城市还不是很了解，
Honestly, at this point, I don't really know much about the city yet,
但我联系了几位对此非常了解的人。
but I've gotten in contact with a couple people who know a lot.
我叫Yap Aford Abrahamsa，嗯，我是一名建筑史学家，
My name is Yap Aford Abrahamsa
在荷兰文化遗产局工作，
and I uh I'm an architectural historian
同时也是阿姆斯特丹自由大学建筑史的特聘教授。
and I work for the cultural heritage agency of the Netherlands
and as an endowed professor of architectural history at the VU University uh in Amsterdam.
>> 我叫Yohim，在阿姆斯特丹出生长大，经营着YouTube频道the present past。
>> My name is Yohim.
我出生在阿姆斯特丹，并在那里长大，
I was born and raised in Amsterdam
我运营着YouTube频道the present past。
and I run the YouTube channel the present past.
>> 我叫Alar Deil，我是一名历史学家，长期在阿姆斯特丹博物馆担任策展人。
>> My name is Alar Deil.
我是一名历史学家，
I'm a historian
长期在阿姆斯特丹博物馆担任策展人。
and I've worked for a long time as a curator at the Amsterdam Museum.
如果你沿着阿姆斯特尔河向海边走，
If you follow the Amstl River to the sea,
就在到达运河带的地方，
just as you get to the canal belt,
你会看到一段异常笔直的河道。
you will see an unnaturally straight stretch of river.
这是这座城市第一条人造运河，也是阿姆斯特丹存在于这里的原因。
This is the first man-made canal in the city,
and it's the reason Amsterdam exists here.
这条运河开凿于12或13世纪，
Dug in the 12th or 13th century,
是为了解决该地区农民长期以来面临的一个问题。
this canal was the solution to a problem that farmers in the region had been dealing with.
他们耕种的是一片低洼、平坦、沼泽地带，
The landscape they farmed was a low-lying, flat, marshy area
由泥炭构成。
made up of pete.
泥炭基本上就是枯叶一层层堆叠，
So Pete is basically dead leaves that have stacked on top of each other,
经过数千年挤压在一起
have been pressed together over the millennia
形成的一种有机质、相当松软的地面。
to make a ground that is um organic and quite soft.
为了让土地适合耕种，需要把水排掉。
To make the land suitable for farming,
the water needed to be drained.
在离城市不远的地方，
There are still places not far from the city
仍然有一些地方可以让你想象当时的景象。
where you can visualize what this would have been like.
但是有一个问题。
But there was a problem.
土地排水的速度跟不上需要。
The land wasn't draining as fast as they needed it to.
它距离出水口太远，处于上游。
It was too far upstream from its outlet.
但如果能把它连接到一个更近的出水口，
But if they could connect it to a closer outlet,
排水速度就会大大加快。
then it could drain much faster.
于是他们就这么做了。
So that's exactly what they did.
修建这条运河将两条河合二为一，
Building this canal turned two rivers into one,
形成了阿姆斯特尔河。
the Amstl.
这解决了排水问题，
And it solved their problem of drainage,
但也带来了一个新问题。
but it also created a new problem.
现在，当风暴潮来临时，
Now, when there was a storm surge,
咸水会被推入上游，威胁农作物。
salty water could be pushed up river and threaten the crops.
这就把我们带到了今天的水坝广场。
And this leads us to modern-day Dam Square.
好的，
Okay,
这个地方叫水坝广场，
this place is called Dam Square
之所以叫水坝广场，
and it's called Dam Square
是因为这里曾经是阿姆斯特尔河上的水坝，
because this used to be the dam in the river Amstel
阿姆斯特丹因此得名，
that gave Amsterdam its name
这座水坝封住了阿姆斯特尔河的河口。
and it closed off the mouth of the river Amsel.
但现在你环顾四周，看不到任何水坝，也看不到任何河流。
But as you look around here now,
you don't see any dam and you don't see any any river.
运河被填平，建起了许多新建筑，
The canals have been filled in and lots of new buildings have been created
船只不见了，
and instead of boats,
取而代之的是有轨电车、汽车和自行车在此穿行。
you see the trams and the cars and the bikes going over this place right now.
虽然现在看起来不起眼，但这座水坝是这座城市的根基。
As unassuming as it may seem now,
this dam was the foundation of the city.
它可以打开让淡水排出，关闭以防止咸水进入。
It could be opened to let the fresh water out
and closed to prevent the salt water from coming in.
>> 泥炭土壤在下沉，
>> The pet soil uh is subsiding
而海水仍然在那里。所以你必须修建水坝和堤防来阻挡海水。
while the sea uh is still there.
所以你必须修建一些水坝和堤防来阻挡海水。
So you have to build um uh dams and dikes to contain the sea.
>> 但水坝的建造产生了更大的影响。
>> But the creation of the dam had a bigger impact.
没有它，
Without it,
阿姆斯特尔河不过是沼泽三角洲中的一条小溪。
the Amstel would have remained a minor river in a swampy delta.
但有了运河和水坝，
But with the canal and the dam,
这里就成了贸易枢纽。
this was now a hub for trade.
>> 阿姆斯特尔河是内陆通道，
>> The river Amsel was inland connection
你可以从这里到达鹿特丹和多德雷赫特。所以你不必航行北海水域——那是个非常危险的地方。
where you could get to Rotterdam and Dor.
所以你不必航行北海水域——那是个非常危险的地方。
So you didn't have to sail the North Sea
which was a very dangerous place.
所以这里是一条河流和一条重要道路的交汇点。
So this was the crossing of a river and an important road.
所以这就是阿姆斯特丹港口形成的地方。
So this is the place
where a lot of where the harbor of Amsterdam um was created.
>> 毫不夸张地说，这座城市的起源就是控制水流。
>> Literally the beginning of the city goes back to controlling the water.
观察城市的第一段发展，
When looking at the first section of the city,
很明显水坝是其中心。
it becomes clear that the dam is at its center.
从那里开始，建筑沿河两岸修建，城市呈现H形。
From there,
buildings were built on both sides of the river
从那里开始，建筑沿河两岸修建，城市呈现H形。
and the city turned into an H shape.
顺便说一句，
By the way,
这张地图的方向是上南下北。
this map is oriented with north on the bottom and south on the top.
>> 今年，
>> This year,
我们正在庆祝阿姆斯特丹建城750周年。
we're celebrating the 750th birthday of Amsterdam.
其实这不完全是建城的日期，因为之前就有人居住，
It's not actually the birthday because people were living here,
但他们在1275年的一份文件中被提及，
but they were mentioned in in 1275 in a document
这份文件授予了居住在Amsterdama的人特许权。
that granted the people living in Amsterdama.
所以，居住在水坝和阿姆斯特尔河建造处的人们获得了在更大范围内进行货物贸易的特权。
So the people living in where the dam and the Amsterl was constructed,
they were granted privileges to trade their goods in the in the bigger area.
效果是加速了发展，
The effect was that it accelerated growth,
吸引了其他人来到这座城市。
that it attracted other people who came to the city.
于是逐渐地，
So gradually, you know,
城市开始扩张，
the city started to expand,
这意味着每次他们都要处理这片沼泽地，修建堤防来阻挡水流。
which meant that every time they had to deal with this marshy lands and and build dikes to to stop the water.
随着城市的发展，
As the city grew,
他们在阿姆斯特尔河两岸各挖了两条额外的排水运河。
they built two additional drainage canals on either side of the Amstl.
而在这片松软的沼泽地上建造并不容易。
And building on this swampy soft soil was not easy.
因为中世纪城市的许多建筑都是木结构的，
Because many of the structures of the medieval city were made of wood
而且几个世纪以来不断有重建，
and because there's been centuries of redevelopment since then
所以那个时期的原始建筑存世的非常少，
very few original buildings from this period exist
但这是其中之一。
but this is one of them.
这是老教堂，
This is the outer the old church
正如其名，它确实很古老。
and well as the name would have it.
这是老教堂。
It's the old church.
它实际上是阿姆斯特丹现存最古老的建筑，
Uh it's actually the oldest building we have left in Amsterdam
坐落在2000多根木桩之上。
and it rests on top of more than 2,000 wooden piles.
这些是建在建筑下面的巨大树干，用来防止建筑下沉陷入泥土。
These are massive tree trunks planted beneath the buildings
to keep them from sinking into the soil.
这在整座城市都相当普遍。
And this was common across the entire city.
>> 我们把木桩打入地下，深度分别是12米、20米或50米，
>> The poles we we we ram into the ground either 12, 20, or 50 m
因为那是三层砂质土壤的所在位置。
because that is the three layers where you actually have a sandy soil.
>> 事实证明这可能是最好的解决方案，
>> It's proven to be probably the best solution,
但也绝对不是完美的。
but it's definitely not perfect.
嗯，建筑确实是固定住了，
Uh the buildings are actually in place,
但阿姆斯特丹的其它地方都一样。
but the rest of Amsterdam is same.
所以街道每隔几年就得翻修一次，
So the the streets have to be redone every few years
每次都得加高。
and they have to be heightened up every time.
>> 除了排水运河，
>> In addition to the drainage canals,
他们还修建了加高的堤防来防止某些地区被洪水淹没，
they would also build raised dikes to prevent certain areas from flooding
其中很多堤防兼做道路，
and a lot of these doubled as roads
它们的名字就清楚地说明了它们原本是什么。
and their names make it quite clear what they were.
>> 我们现在走在zyke上，
>> We're now walking on uh zyke,
字面意思就是"海堤"。
which literally translates to sea dyke.
所以这里就是城市旧堤防的所在地。
So this is literally where the old dyke of the city used to be.
如果你看地图，
And if you look at the map,
可以看到这条曲线围绕在周围。
you can see this this curve around it.
如果你只是沿着海岸线
If you're just tracing the outline of the coast
来划定堤防的走向，
where you're going to put your dyke,
它永远不可能是笔直的。
it's never going to be super straight.
所以你真的可以看到高度差。
So you can really see the height difference.
如果你看那边，看到那些在喝啤酒的人，他们确实是在一个不同的水平面上。
If you look over there and you see the people drinking a beer,
they're literally on a different level.
所以，如果你站在一片高地，就像我们现在在Z D上一样，那就意味着它是人造的。
So if you are on a patch of elevation like we're here now on the Z D,
it means it's it is man-made.
这不是自然形成的地形。
It's not a it's an unnatural occurrence.
>> 中世纪城市的边界以这两条运河为标志，
>> The boundary of the medieval city is marked by these two canals
它们也是城市的护城河。
which also served as its moat.
>> 阿姆斯特尔河与水坝广场，两边各有一条运河，
>> It's Amsel with dam square and two canals on either side
然后在外面建起了新城墙和新运河，
and then a new city wall was built around it with a new canal
这基本上就是中世纪时期的城市结构。
and that's basically the medieval structure of the city.
当你把中世纪城市和运河带的其他部分对比来看，市中心不规则、蜿蜒的街道与之外更规划化的区域之间有明显的视觉差异。
When you look at the medieval city versus the rest of the canal belt,
there's a distinct visual difference between the irregular windy roads of the center of the city versus the more planned areas beyond it.
所以当你在城市中漫步时，
So when you're walking around the city,
每一次扩张之间都有清晰的区别。
there's a clear distinction between each of these expansions.
在我们现在站的地方看得特别清楚，
And you can see it where we're standing really clearly
因为这条水、这条运河现在只是运河系统的一部分，
because this water, this canal is now just part of the canal system,
但它曾经是护城河。
but it used to be the moat.
而城门就在我们刚才看的那个地方。
And the city gate is back there that we were looking at.
但这一边，你可以看到一整排建筑的实墙。
But this side you can see just a solid wall of all the buildings.
而这一边，你可以看到道路切入每一个街区。
And on this side you can see the roads cutting in to each of these blocks.
还有两座那个时代的建筑我想指出来。
There are two other structures from this era that I want to point out.
那边是中世纪城市的边界，
Over there is the edge of the medieval city
你可以看到一段至今保存的中世纪城墙。
and you can see one part of the medieval city wall that's still standing.
它被称为store。
It's called the store.
这里常被称为"哭泣塔"，因为水手们就是从这个地方告别家人，踏上数月或数年的漫长航行。
This is often referred to as the weeping tower
because it was from this spot that sailors would leave their families for months or years on long voyages.
如果你沿着旧城墙的路径走一小段，就会来到另一座幸存的建筑——旧城门。
If you follow just a short way down the path of the old city wall,
you'll come to another surviving building, the old city gate.
那么，你看那边，可以看到写着restaurant cafe的地方。
So, if you look over there,
you can see where it says restaurant cafe.
嗯，
Um,
那实际上就是旧城门所在的位置。
that is actually where the old gate to the city used to be.
就像树有年轮来标识其年龄一样，
It's like a tree has rings to indicate its age.
城市也有年轮。
而城市也有年轮。
And a city also has rings.
我们现在就站在其中一个年轮上，
And we're standing right here on one of these rings
展示着城市的中世纪部分，
showing the medieval part of the city
而那边则是城市更为现代的部分。
and outside there the more modern part of the city.
世界变化很快，
The world changes fast
你要为之做好准备。
and you want to be ready for when it does.
这就是债务令人恐惧的原因。
And that's what can make debt so scary.
但它既令人恐惧，也同样普遍。
But it's as scary as it is common.
所以当PDS debt联系我赞助今天的视频时，
So that's why when PDS debt reached out to sponsor today's video
我看到他们在Better Business Bureau上获得了A+评级，
and I saw that they have an A+ with the Better Business Bureau
在Google上有超过一千条正面评价，
as well as over a thousand positive reviews on Google,
这让我有信心，
that made me feel confident
如果你正面临债务问题，这确实是一个可以帮到你的服务。
that this is a service that could really help you if you're dealing with debt.
他们已经帮助了成千上万的人摆脱信用卡、贷款和高息陷阱。
They've helped hundreds of thousands of people break free from credit cards and loans and highinterest traps.
PDS Debt会根据你独特的财务状况量身定制计划。
PDS Debt crafts a personalized plan designed just for your unique financial situation.
他们的职责是帮你省更多钱，
Their job is to help you save more,
更快还清债务，
pay off your debt faster,
把更多的钱留在你的口袋里，
and keep more money in your pocket where it belongs,
而且没有最低信用评分的要求。
and there's no minimum credit score requirement.
如果我有债务问题，
If I were dealing with debt,
我绝对会考虑这个服务。
this would be a service I would absolutely be looking into.
所以，
So,
你距离开始无债生活只有30秒。
you're just 30 seconds away from beginning your journey to being debtfree.
获取免费评估，
Get your free assessment
在pdsdebt.com/danielststeiner找到最适合你的方案。
and find the best option for you at pdsdebt.com/danielststeiner.
网址是pdsdebt.com/danielsteiner。
That's pdsdebt.com/danielsteiner.
pds.com/danielststeiner。
pds.com/danielststeiner.
回到关于阿姆斯特丹地图的视频。
Back to the video about Amsterdam's map.
宗教改革对欧洲的影响
It's kind of hard to overstate the impact
怎么强调都不过分。
that the Reformation had on Europe.
不仅是直接影响，
Not just directly,
还有它引发的一系列连锁事件。
but also the chain of events that it caused.
宗教改革在整个欧洲引发了战争。
The Reformation sparked wars across Europe.
在教皇的支持下，
Backed by the Pope,
国王和皇帝派军队去镇压反对天主教统治的城市。
kings and emperors sent out armies to crush cities that opposed Catholic rule.
起初，阿姆斯特丹仍然忠于天主教的西班牙，
At first, Amsterdam stayed loyal to Catholic Spain,
但到了1578年，它正式成为了新教城市。
but by 1578, it officially became Protestant.
>> 这被称为Alterasi。
>> It was called the Alterasi.
所以，
So,
我们不断接纳来自欧洲各地的新教难民。
we're welcoming sort of Protestant refugees also from all over Europe.
>> 而这件事发生在安特卫普陷落之前，
>> And this happened just before the fall of Antworp,
当时西班牙人占领了低地国家中最大、最富裕的城市。
the moment when the Spanish captured the largest and wealthiest city in the low countries.
安特卫普落入西班牙人手中，
And fell into the into Spanish hands
近一半的人口离开了这座城市，
and almost half of the population left the city
阿姆斯特丹接替成为荷兰乃至西北欧的主要贸易中心。
and Amsterdam took over as the main trade hub in the Netherlands and even in in the northwest Europe.
于是从那时起，阿姆斯特丹开始以非常非常快的速度增长，
So at that time Amsterdam started to grow really really really fast
新的港区被建起来，
and new harbor areas were created
而且必须精心设计以容纳大量涌入的人口。
and they really had to be designed to accommodate this large influx of people.
新城墙在更远的地方修建起来，
A new city wall was built further out
原来的城墙被拆除了。
and the original one was torn down.
这实际上在我们之前看的那座旧城门周围创造了一片空地，
This actually created an open space around that original city gate that we were looking at,
现在被用作城市市场中心的驿站，
which would now be used as a way station in the center of a city market,
这一点在该地区的名字中仍有体现。
which is still referenced in the name of the area.
在城市的东侧，增加了一条运河；在西侧，建了一个规模大得多的港口。
On the east side of the city, a canal was added,
and on the west side, a much more robust harbor.
这个港口区域是地图上最直观的例子，展示了阿姆斯特丹即将发生的变化。
This harbor area is the perfect visual example on a map
of what was about to happen to Amsterdam.
荷兰人要把他们拥有的海军力量转变为全球性的势力。
The Dutch were going to take the naval strength they had
and turn it into a global power.
如果你看地图，
If you look at the map,
可以看到阿姆斯特丹大致位于欧洲东部——从芬兰到丹麦到波兰——和南部西班牙之间。
you can see that Amsterdam is sort of between the eastern part of Europe, Finland to to Denmark to Poland
and the southern parts, Spain.
所以阿姆斯特丹处于绝佳的中间位置。
So Amsterdam is perfectly positioned in the middle.
此外还有第二个有利位置。
And there's a second nice position.
你可以看到，阿姆斯特丹实际上位于欧洲巨大河流三角洲的尽头。
You can see actually that Amsterdam is at the end of a huge European delta of rivers.
河流纵横交错，贯穿整个欧洲大陆。
crisscrossing all the way through the continent.
凭借这一地理位置，阿姆斯特丹迎来了荷兰黄金时代。
By capitalizing on this position,
Amsterdam ushered in the Dutch golden age.
阿姆斯特丹成为了世界金融中心。
Amsterdam became the financial capital of the world.
正是在这些条件之下，
And it was under these circumstances
现代证券交易所诞生了。
that the modern stock exchange was born.
正是在这个时代，
It was during this era
我们所熟知的运河带被建了起来。
that the canal belt we know was created.
荷兰东印度公司和后来的荷兰西印度公司相继成立，
The Dutch East India Company and later the Dutch West India Company were established
开始从世界各地掠夺资源。
and began extracting resources from all over the world.
荷兰黄金时代不仅仅是金钱。
The Dutch Golden Age was more than just money.
那是一个科学进步的时代，
It was an era of scientific advancement,
是伦勃朗和维米尔等艺术大师涌现的时代，
an outpouring of art from people like Rembrandt and Vermeier,
与之密切相关的，还有制图学。
and closely related, mapping.
荷兰人在制图方面变得非常出色。
The Dutch got really good at mapping.
17世纪出版的最大、最昂贵的书是一本由扬·布劳出版的600页地图集。
The largest and most expensive book published in the 17th century was a 600page atlas published by Yan Blau.
它展现了荷兰黄金时代鼎盛时期制图的精确与品质。
It displayed the precision and quality of mapmaking at the height of the Dutch Golden Age.
随着阿姆斯特丹在国际上的地位提升，
As Amsterdam grew in global prominence,
其面临的外部威胁也随之增加。
so did its risk of outside threat.
被西班牙、英格兰和法国包围，
Surrounded by Spain, England, and France,
显然需要建造防御工事和运河来保护城市。
it became clear that fortifications and canals would need to be built to protect the city.
>> 城市在扩张，
>> The city was expanding
发展得很好。
and was doing well.
所以很多人，比如来自德国、斯堪的纳维亚的人，来到这里工作，
So also a lot of people from from Germany, for instance, from Scandinavia came here to work
修建这些运河，
to build these canals uh
在开往亚洲的船上工作。
to work on the ships that were sailing to uh Asia.
所以城市在17世纪增长得非常非常快。
So the city grew very very fast in the 17th century.
>> 解决方案由城市测量师和城市工程师共同制定。
>> The solution was drawn up under the city surveyor and the city engineer.
这个计划将使阿姆斯特丹的面积扩大一倍。
The plan would double the size of Amsterdam.
街道和运河按照精心设计的网格和弧形模式布局，适应了沼泽地带的地形。
Streets and canals followed a carefully designed grid and arc pattern
adapted to the swampy terrain.
但存在一个风险。
But there was a risk.
城市的人口会继续以同样的速度增长吗？
Would the city continue to grow in population at the same rate?
如果他们建了这一切
What if they built all this
但没人来怎么办？
and no one came?
所以解决方案是分两部分进行。
So the solution was to do it in two parts.
>> 这几乎就像一个雨刷。
>> It's almost like a windscreen wiper.
你看城市像一个雨刷一样扩张，到某一点就停止了。
You see the city expanding like a like a windscreen
and at one point it's it stops.
>> 在这个规划中，有两个不同的区域。
>> And within this plan there are two distinct sections.
第一个是一系列运河。
The first is a series of canals.
这些运河彼此之间的距离各不相同，
These were positioned at different distances from each other
为最富有的运河豪宅留出一排，拥有最大的花园面积，
to create one row for the wealthiest canal houses with the largest garden areas
为稍逊一筹的富人留出另一排。
and another for the slightly less wealthy.
这些区域被特意设计成与扩张区的其余部分——
These were very much intended to be separated from the rest of the expansion,
约旦区——分隔开来。
the Jordan.
这个区域是为下层阶级准备的，让他们在那里进行有气味、嘈杂的工作。
This area was for the lower class
to keep their smelly, noisy work.
但到他们开始建造时，
But by the time they started building this,
遇到了一个问题。
they had a problem.
涌入城市的移民太多了，
There had been so many immigrants moving to the city
许多人就在城墙外的空地上随意建房。
that many of them had just started building on random plots outside the city wall.
这就像一个巨大的人员拼图，他们必须把人们搬迁安置。
This turned into like like a giant puzzle of people
they had to move around.
所以他们的做法是在现有城市旁边修建运河。
So what they did was they created the canals next to the existing city.
许多已经住在那里的人
And many of the people who are already living there,
被迁移到了同样被城市化的农业用地上。
they moved out into the agricultural land that was also urbanized.
那就像是一个非正式的城市化区域，
It was like a a phob informally urbanized area
他们不得不从运河的位置搬出，为运河腾出空间。
and they had to move out from the canal to make room for the canals.
他们被迁往约旦区。
They moved them out into the Yordan area.
而后来约旦区的结构无法再改变，
Uh and then the structure of this Yordan area couldn't be changed anymore
因为建筑已经部分存在了。
because part of the building was already there.
所以在它真正成为城市的一部分之前，就已经城市化了
So it was already urbanized
这就是为什么你在地图上看到这些不同的结构。
before it really became part of the city.
And that is why you see these different structures on the map.
>> 你可以看到约旦区道路的角度和宽度与农业模式完全吻合。
>> You can see that the angle and width of the roads in the Jordan area perfectly match the farming pattern.
这是城市增长速度的直接结果。
This is a direct result of how fast the city was growing.
>> 所以说这其实是阿姆斯特丹的郊区。
>> So this was really an outskirt of Amsterdam.
那里没有自治市集。
There were no burrow fairs.
你无法穿行，也没有人需要穿行，因为那里就像是城市的边缘。
You couldn't go through and nobody needed to go through because it was like the edge of the city.
运河区不允许任何工业，因为那里是住宅区，分区规定非常严格。
No industries were allowed in the canal zone
because this was the residential zone and zoning was very strict.
所以所有的工业都被推到了约旦区，
So all the industries were pushed out into uh the Yordan area
而约旦区当时地势更低。
which at the same time was uh lying lower.
所以运河也更浅，水流根本不流通。
So also the canals were uh less deep and like the the profile the the water didn't flow through it at all.
水是静止的，
So the water was still
所以这个规划的分割造成了一个非常严重的环境问题。
so there was a very big environmental problem that was created by this fragmentation of the plan.
>> 这座城市一定臭气熏天。
>> The city must have stunk.
我读过的所有关于这里的东西，都提到这座城市的味道有多糟糕。
Everywhere I've read about this, it's mentioned how bad the city smelled.
它一直被当作露天下水道使用，直到1930年。
It was used as an open sewer all the way to 1930.
所以，我觉得城市里没有哪个地方是不臭的。
So, I don't think there was anywhere in the city that wasn't smelly.
但因为约旦区由一堆木结构建筑组成，而且密集地挤在一起，
But because Jordan was made up of a bunch of wooden structures that were really densely packed together,
城市中发生的许多火灾都集中在这个区域。
many of the fires that did happen in the city happened in this area.
而在它的另一侧是新的棱堡城墙和护城河，
And on its other side was the new bastioned wall and moat,
其走向在现代地图上仍然清晰可见。
the path of which is still visible in a modern map.
等他们建成时，
By the time they built this,
这里已经完全住满了。
it was already fully populated.
人口增长略有放缓，
Population growth had slowed slightly,
但仍在增长，
but it was still growing,
荷兰人仍在扩张他们的殖民地。
and the Dutch were still expanding their colonies.
于是他们决定继续执行计划，
So, they decided to continue on with their plan,
完成环绕城市的星形棱堡环。
completing the full star-shaped bastion ring around the city.
但就在建成仅仅10年后
But just 10 years after it was finished being constructed
迎来了所谓的灾难之年。
came what would be known as the year of disaster.
来自英格兰和法国的攻击标志着黄金时代的终结。
A moment of attack from England and France that marked the end of the golden age.
人口停止增长，城市发展冻结。
The population stopped growing and urban development froze.
>> 经济衰退的好处是阿姆斯特丹城内出现了大量绿地。
>> The upside of economic downturn was that there was a lot of greenery in inside Amsterdam.
阿姆斯特丹的治理者、市政府，
The burglar masters of Amsterdam, the Amsterdam government,
他们选择尽量善加利用。
they chose to make the best of it.
由于这些地块无法作为建筑用地出售，
And as they couldn't sell these as building plots,
他们选择将其作为花园地块出租。
they uh chose to rent them as um garden plots.
这个区域被称为Plantagia，
The area was called the Plantagia,
我们翻译为种植园，
which we translate as plantation,
城内的一大片绿地。
a big green area inside the city.
这片种植园区、这个Plantagia唯一的遗迹是名为artistis的动物园，
The only remnant of this plantation area, this Plantagia, is the zoo called artistis,
其余部分都已被分割出售。
but the rest was parcel out and sold.
阿姆斯特丹的现代发展已经跳出了运河带。
Amsterdam's modern development has jumped the canal belt.
但正是黄金时代铸就了这座城市的标志性根基。
But it was the golden age that forged the iconic foundation of the city.
在19世纪，经过200年的停滞之后，
In the 19th century, after 200 years of stagnation,
一切重新开始了
everything started again
随着北海运河的修建，
with the creation of the North Sea Canal,
为阿姆斯特丹开辟了通往北海的新通道和通往世界的新连接，可以容纳更大的船只。
which gave Amsterdam a new link to the North Sea and a new connection to the world for bigger ships.
这给港口带来了巨大的推动力。
So that gave a big impulse to the harbor.
与此同时，中央车站也建了起来，
And at the same time the central station was created
他们在一个位于港口前方的人工岛上建造了中央车站。
and they built central station on an artificial island in front of the harbor.
>> 这座中央车站的建造确实切断了城市与那个港口的连接。
>> The construction of this central station really cut off the city from that harbor.
>> 关于车站的位置有过很大的争议。
>> There were huge discussions concerning about the location of this station.
实际上，是荷兰政府而不是阿姆斯特丹市政府做出了在那边建中央车站的决定。
So actually the Dutch government not the Amsterdam government took the decision to create central station over there.
>> 多年来，为了使市中心更加可达，人们做了很多努力。
>> There have been many efforts over the years
to make the city center more accessible.
他们开辟了一条穿城而过的街道——strat city hall street，
They created a breakthrough street strat city hall street
将现在的水坝广场上的皇宫（曾经是市政厅）
which connects the now palace on dam square which used to be city hall
与19世纪城墙之外正在开发的新区域连接起来。
to the new areas that were being developed beyond the city walls in the 19th century.
所以这条街是19世纪80年代的。
So this street is from the from the 1880s.
这是一组相当不错的19世纪建筑群，由Fronent建筑事务所设计，
This is like a quite a nice ensemble of 19th century building by the Fronent architectural firm
我认为他们是阿姆斯特丹19世纪最好的建筑事务所之一。
which was one of the best I think in Amsterdam's 19th century >> architecture scene.
是的。但尽管发生了所有这些变化和提议，
Yeah. >> But despite all of the changes and proposals,
阿姆斯特丹仍然保持了它的魅力。
Amsterdam has still managed to keep its charm.
>> 如果你在运河上，
>> If you're on the canals,
你的视线永远不会延伸得太远。
you never have a line of sight that goes on for too long.
这让它感觉很温馨。
And that makes it feel cozy.
因为如果你将其与像巴黎这样的地方相比，
Because if you compare that to a place like Paris
巴黎在19世纪被彻底重新设计过，很明显它不是为了人的尺度而打造的，它有不同的理念。
where they completely redesigned the city in the 19th century
但阿姆斯特丹仍然非常非常人性化。
and it's very clear that it's not tailored to to a person but it has a different idea.
But Amsterdam is still very very human.
不得不说，在制作了所有这些关于纽约、关于新阿姆斯特丹的视频之后，
I have to say after making all of the videos that I have made about New York and about New Amsterdam
现在身在这里并思考这些，
and now being here and thinking about that,
让我不禁好奇：如果英国人没有接管的话，纽约会是什么样子。
it's making me wonder what New York could have been like if the English hadn't taken over.
可能会是一座截然不同的城市。
could have been a very different city.
也许就像这里一样。
Might have felt like this.
>> 对我来说，这总是一种穿越历史的感觉。
>> For me, it's always a feeling of, you know, actually walking through history.
你从城市的中心、从城市的起源越是向外走，
The further you move away from the center, from the origins of the city,
就越是在穿越历史，越接近当代的城市。
you move through history and you get more and more to contemporary city.
>> 如果你不能亲身走一遍，也许现在你可以在地图上读出来。
>> And if you can't go walk physically through it,
maybe now you can read it on its map.
非常感谢Yap、Yakam和Anmarie帮助我制作这期视频。
Huge thanks to Yap, Yakam, and Anmarie for helping me with this video.
我在描述中放了他们所有作品的链接，
I've put links in the description to all of their work,
你们可以去查看。
so you can go check that out.
对在座的各位，
And to the rest of you,
感谢你们的观看。
thank you for watching.
如果你喜欢这个视频，
If you liked this,
请点赞。
please hit the like button.
如果你还没有订阅，请订阅本频道。
Please subscribe to the channel if you haven't.
我们刚刚突破了30万订阅，这真的很令人激动。
We just hit 300,000, so that's really exciting.
分享给你的朋友和家人。这对我帮助很大，让我能够继续制作这些视频。
Share with your friends and family. It helps me a lot so that I can keep making these.
如果你想通过Patreon支持我，
And if you want to support me on my Patreon,
链接也在下面。但无论如何，我们下个视频很快再见。
that's also linked below.
But either way, I'll see you guys in another video very soon.
再见。
Peace.